So welcome, everybody, to the
final day of this workshop.
So essentially up to now we
have been dealing with what's
known as the forward problem.
We have been building models
and then simulating them forward
in time and plotting
simulation results.
But for this last
session, we will
work on the inverse problem.
And that's it.
Given a model and
given some data,
how can we retrieve or
fit the model to the data
so we can retrieve model
parameters that actually when
the model simulates, then
the result of the simulation
matches that data?
And dynamic causal modeling
is a way of doing this.
And it can essentially
accommodate
any type of time series that we
typically use in neuroscience.
So most common cases will
be electrophysiological data
or imaging data.
So fMRI needs experiments
heavily make use of DCM.
And as I said, the challenge
is to find the best model
parameters for your
model to make your model
look like the data.
And DCM does that in
a Bayesian manner.
It follows at least
this Bayesian formalism.
And I'll talk more
about this in a second.
And it's using
state space models.
I'll show you an example
of state space model.
But you can think of them
as a discretized version
of the differential equations.
In state space models, we have
the state at one time point
and how that depends on states
at the previous time points.
So we have this almost
discrete evolution in steps.
And it's also a
method that gives us
back effective Connectivity
and especially if you're
coming from the
neuroimaging field,
you will probably be
more familiar with this.
But what do we mean by
effective connectivity
is essentially a
metric of connectivity
between regions of the brain
that is driven by a model.
So it is more than
just correlations
between those regions.
So for instance
here on the right,
we see some voxel-based
activity out
of three regions in the brain.
And typically, an
easy thing to do
is to calculate the functional
connectivity between them, which
is just taking correlations
between pairs of these,
and then seeing how well
correlated or anti-correlated
these regions are.
But that's a purely
statistical measure.
With DCM, we add a
model into the mix.
And this model comes
from our hypothesis
about the dynamics of
each one of these regions.
So when we actually build
the final graph of the model,
as you can see here
with these four regions,
and we add any input, like
the U1's and the U2's here,
the inputs can be either
external inputs completely
external to the brain.
Or they just can be inputs
from inside the brain
that we're not modeling,
like we did yesterday
with the Poisson spike trains.
Those spike trains are
coming from inside the brain.
It's just they're
coming from populations
that we don't model explicitly.
So when you build a model, like
this a more biophysical model,
and you feed this model to
the data, what you get back
is the effective
connectivity, and that's
a more reliable measure, I would
say, of the actual connectivity
between these regions
because it doesn't just
rely on summary statistics.
It looks into the dynamics of
the neuron over time and figures
out how they are connected.
So as I was saying, DCM, and
particularly the spectral DCM
that we will look into now, is
built of state space models.
And here you can see an
example of a state space
model expressed as a
differential equation
at this time.
And this is a bilinear
model because it
has this the linear term,
which is the a times x.
But it also has this bilinear
term of the u times v times x.
So as I said, u's our inputs,
or inputs from populations
that we don't explicitly model.
c is the input weights.
b, this bilinear
term is essentially
the effective connectivity as
it is modulated by the inputs.
That's why we have
the input multiplier.
And a is the
effective connectivity
between regions given no input.
This is independent of inputs.
And the main goal of
DCM is to give you
back these a and b matrices.
So this is how you can tell
how your network is actually
structured by looking
into the a if you care
about the case of connectivity
without any inputs
or looking into the
combination of a and b,
if you also care about
some specific inputs.
Now, the assumptions
that it makes
is that it assumes that
there is a weak stationarity
in your signal.
And that means that the cross
spectral density, essentially,
for any finite amount of
measured time that you have,
say, in a bold experiment
that remains constant,
it assumes bilinearity.
And this is essentially the
introduction of this b matrix
here, where it allows for this
input modulated connectivity.
And also it assumes
Gaussianity, and that basically
means that all of the
parameters that we're
fitting during the
DCM process, we
assume that they come from
a normal distribution.
And that's, in other words,
the Laplace approximation.
Now, here I'd like to show
you essentially on the left
how a typical pipeline of
DCM works on both data.
And on the right, we have the
equivalent snippets of code
from Neuroblox itself.
So we start from the
actual neural dynamics.
And our default is to
use this neural mass
model, which is exactly this
equation here or written
in Neuroblox.
Here you see this
dx equals to jcn
because, as you see in previous
days, jcn can be any input.
So as we build the
circuit stitch together
multiple of these
linear mass models,
essentially we will build
the a matrix and the b matrix
and any c matrix if
that's also included.
And now below that,
so the result of this
is some population
average neural activity.
This is just a
neural mass model.
But then we move into the
hemodynamic state equations.
So this is what is
called the balloon model.
So this model will
essentially model the dilation
of blood vessels, and
it will model blood flow
in the brain, given
parameters of the neural mass,
specifically for this
region that we're
modeling with the neural mass.
And on top of the balloon model,
we have this the BOLD signal.
So essentially, we take the
results of the balloon model
and we transform them to
BOLD, which is actually
a quantity measured in fMRI.
So this is essentially
the pipeline
that helps us move from a neural
mass scale all the way up,
essentially, the
hierarchy to BOLD.
And we can relate our model,
our biophysical model,
it can be any blocks here
to actual imaging data.
And here I'm also showing
you the symbolic way
that we write the
balloon equations
to see that it actually
matches the math quite easily.
So of course, the
balloon model is not
the only model that can actually
transform neural activity
to BOLD.
Eventually you can replace
this with other models.
So this is what we call
an observer blocks.
Now, in order to solve
the inverse problem
and get back the true parameters
for your network in DCM,
we perform variational
Bayesian approach.
So in other words,
that means that we
assume a specific
family of specific shape
of the distribution
for the posterior.
And the posterior
distribution in Bayesian terms
is always the distribution of
the parameters given the data.
And this is Bayes' rule.
That's equal to a
likelihood function, that
is, the probability of the data
given parameters and any prior
that we have over
the parameters.
So that's the p of probability.
And yeah, this product
is the important thing.
And this product is divided by
this normalizing factor, which
is the probability of data i.
But in practical applications,
because the probability of data
is something very hard to
calculate because that assumes
no specific parameters, that's
the probability of all data
in your experiment, we apply
this variational Bayes' trick,
which helps us circumvent
essentially the computation
of this because we assume a
specific shape of the posterior.
Now, after making
this assumption,
we will perform essentially
an optimization.
And this optimization
is to maximize
the negative free energy,
which, in other words,
in machine learning literature,
you can also find this
as the evidence lower bound.
It's this quantity
right here, which,
if you expand on the log a
bit, you can see that it also--
it's the same as the
Kullback-Leibler divergence,
which is a function that
measures the distance
between two distributions.
And in this case,
it's the distance
between q, which is
our assumption of what
the posterior looks like, and
essentially, the marginal--
sorry.
It's not the marginal.
This is the combination
essentially of the likelihood
and the priors together.
So essentially
we're trying to make
this what we have
assumed for this quantity
as close to possible as the
product of these two here.
And in order to
do this, we apply
this Levenberg-Marquardt
optimization.
So this is what was recommended
by the original DCM work.
And it does perform better
than other approaches
like a Gauss-Newton
method, which
is very common
optimization method.
But as you can
see, for instance,
in the case of this
posterior distribution,
if you apply
Gauss-Newton and you
start from a point of no
high probability density,
then this method can drift away,
and it can lead you astray,
basically.
But if you follow the
Levenberg-Marquardt,
even from the same
initial point,
it actually manages to find the
place of the highest probability
mass, which is what you would
want ideally from this method.
Now, there are different
types of the DCM analysis.
The earliest one we had the
deterministic DCM, which
included simple state
space models like the one
that I showed you,
then stochastic DCM,
which can include
nonlinearities and also
include, well,
stochastic terms in it.
But exactly because
of the introduction
of the stochasticity, that
became computationally much
heavier.
So in other words, it's
impossible to run a model
with many different
regions in this model
in any reasonable
amount of time.
A regression-based
DCM, on the other hand,
is very fast because,
in regression DCM,
we replace the state space
model with some simple GLM.
That's the generalized
linear model.
So we do away with a lot of
the differential equations
so that that's much
faster to compute.
And the spectral DCM is
somewhere in between the others.
It allows for stochasticity.
In terms of the
speed of running,
it's in between
the deterministic
and the regression.
But it maintains
biophysical relevance
because we still keep
the state space models.
And as I was saying,
you can add any blocks
that you want to for any one
of your regions in your model.
Now in Neuroblox, we have our
own implementation of DCM.
DCM, it's also originally
comes from SPM,
which is a statistical package,
I believe originally in Matlab,
but there's also a
dual implementation.
And here I'm just showing
you some performance graphs,
where you can see that our
implementation in Julia,
using modeling toolkit--
that's in green-- or
using not modeling toolkit
but the nonsymbolic way of
writing differential equations
but still using automatic
differentiation, which
is actually the novelty here.
The original implementation
of DCM in SPM
does not have any
automatic differentiation.
So both of these
implementations, the towers,
the orange and green are much
faster than the original one
in Matlab.
But they're also faster
than the original algorithm
implemented in Julia.
And the importance is that
the orange and green overlap.
So that tells us
that, even though we
use modeling toolkit,
which is the symbolic way,
we don't lose performance over
the nonsymbolic way of writing
differential equations.
And essentially, this is in
spirit with modeling toolkit
and in spirit with
everything else
that we've seen in Neuroblox.
We wrote SP-DCM to
be very modular.
So you can essentially follow
this entire pipeline, which you
will in the exercises as well.
And you can replace parts
of it with different parts.
For instance, when you define
your neural mask block,
you can just replace, say,
this set of two equations
with your own block.
When you build the
circuit, of course,
you have the freedom
to build any circuit
that you want that comes from
your hypothesis about which
regions of the brain
you think are implicated
in your experiment.
You can provide any
measurements that you
like, be it electrophysiological
ones or imaging ones.
And then we give you the option
of doing variational inference
with automatic differentiation
and with the Laplace
approximation and also
give you out some metrics
so you can tell whether
the optimization worked
or how much you should trust
your results essentially.
And this is also
published from our group,
so you can check this
preprint as well.
So finally, I would like to
talk about model selection
because say that we make an
assumption about the network
that our experiments should
stimulate or so the network
that should be involved.
But we don't exactly
have the connectivity
within that network, so we can
try different configurations.
So here you can see
the results of trying
three different configurations
and comparing them.
And to do the comparison
we essentially print out
the free energy functional.
So larger values for the
negative free energy are better.
So the blue line is the ground
truth here, the ground truth
model, because this comes
from simulated data.
So we used the blue one
to generate some data
and then fit all three.
And then the orange is a
version of the ground truth
model with just one
connection removed.
This was a model
with three regions,
but the orange one has the
connection from region 2
to region 1 removed.
And model 3 has this connection
and also another connection
from 2 to 3 removed.
So as you can see,
the comparison
works because as you move
further and further away
from the ground truth model,
the free energy functional
becomes worse and worse.
And this is the
metric that we apply
to do model selection at
the end of the DCM process.
So this was my final slide.
So you can navigate
to the final session,
spectral dynamic
causal modeling,
and open the relevant
notebook DCM.
And yeah, feel free
to ask any questions.
Thanks.